okay right hi tom
excellent to finally get a chance to
catch up again
the last time we had a longer
conversation with your majorca
and just got off the paddleboards that
you used when you were here
um and we we did some sub-paddling
together so i'm really excited to get a
chance to
talk with you again and um
i've just done a bit of research on you
and it actually felt like
so much like you've done so much that
briefly i had this doubt and i was like
is that the same tom duncan because um
it's really quite impressive like
like i've unearthed some work that you
did with the
permaculture research institute and and
then really got into
[Music]
working on water and healing waterways
and
ecological restoration of waterways
and um yeah i won't take the whole story
in advance but i would love for you to
tell a little bit
your story how did you get into this and
um
[Music]
and you the trajectory you took to end
up
being the ceo of earth bank now
yeah well thank you so much uh it's
great to be back here
uh with you daniel uh you know chatting
again
i remember when we're in myocar and uh
uh
chatting and out on the ocean together
it was a
special time to really uh be able to
zoom out on what's really important and
zoom in as well
and um thank you for this opportunity uh
you know regeneration uh
as a personal journey for me i guess you
know
what has been my journey in this i
started off as a boy growing up on a
farm
you know in rural australia um and
we we had a fairly interesting situation
that
our extended family joined together and
together
uh as a collective purchased uh several
farms so there was five families
um that would come together and as a
result we
you know we would move from farm to farm
over the year um a little bit like
nomadic gypsies
um to to essentially be part of the
harvest of each one and we built
up um the most southern ranging uh
uh organic avocado farm in australia
um until that time no one had planted uh
avocado trees as fast health as my
grandparents had
planted and my parents and aunties and
uncle and
uh so that was you know i guess i was
introduced to
sort of innovation on the land at an
early age um
you know from when i was born we were so
i grew up in that environment um of sort
of innovation on the land and uh
it was a very very dry environment uh
the organic
avocado uh portraits and uh so we had to
do a lot of innovation
you know the first kind of shelter belts
um the first kind of
uh drip irrigation systems um you know
this was in the in the 70s when i was
growing up there
the late 70s and um early 80s so
so that was my sort of introduction and
then we started growing
kiwi fruit up in the mountainous region
on a coast which was very wet and almost
tropical um in its rainfall pattern and
you know
uh we had every deadly uh species known
to a human kind on that surrounded by
like just completely wild
uh country you know beautiful we were
sort of right in the middle of a
national park essentially
up on a mountain and it turned out that
mountain was actually very very sacred
to the local
first nation um and so we
would work uh the fields uh
work our kiwi vines with um local
indigenous communities who we took
on into our collective farm as
colleagues
and the sort of super flat structures we
had was
quite interesting for them um and
they kind of encouraged us to come into
their world a little bit
and so we got introduced at a young age
to
the traditional ways of being and
knowing that they
uh had in their lives their worldview
their spirituality and cosmology
and so we kind of took a bit of a dive
into
their world literally um we got taken to
um these beautiful sacred waterholes
up in the mountains which are
traditionally used
for teaching so they're teaching sites
uh
where essentially boys become men and so
generally the the trial that you get
put through is that you know you will uh
you know get fully painted up go through
the traditional corroboree
which is essentially reenacting the
cosmology of that region and the
cosmos universe everything um and
you then sort of over a period of
several weeks you'll wind your way
through the landscape
following the waterways all the way up
to the source
now the source of where the water is
coming from that's
where they believe their ancestors are
all living there
um and so the act when you get there
you you're covered in pain still as
most of it's fallen off it's okay uh you
get there um
you go through ceremony and then you
essentially dive
you it's i call it the world's oldest
uh waterfall like slippery dip in the
world like it was australia being one of
the most
ancient continents around
this rock is just ancient basalt you
know smooth as
maybe like four meters and you get into
this
slippery dip this water and you get shot
out
like you get projectile thrown out into
this giant pool
which is where the ancestors live there
that's the ancestor
and and the last bit of ochre that's on
your body which is kind of x-ray vision
sort of like showing your inner body
sort of dissolves
into the ancestor pool and you you come
out and you're now a man when you come
out of that pool
so and you've managed to survive you
know
walking the landscape um so that's kind
of
what i guess is part of my formative
years of
you know what makes me me about my
experiences
yeah how old were you when you went
through that initiation process
so so we started going to that
site uh when i was just a
very small uh like a toddler actually
was when i first started going to the
site as a child
and then as you get older and older uh
you know you get
um and i didn't go through the entire
ceremony that's
um i went through a fairly limited
ceremony with
um you know the elders are only able to
take you so far um as they're um
authorized by the rest of their first
nation so we went through a limited
ceremony of
of that though and it's pretty
incredible um
um to experience and um
they used to be called dreaming camps uh
held by elder that you know we would
learn the songs
of all of the the uh different species
so we would learn the the
the name of uh the species and how to
sing it
and so when you sing it you walk along
the rivers and you renew the song lines
uh and so you know that the species in a
very intimate way that you you can
say the true name um and you know it's a
very ancient
you know tens of thousands of years old
culture
it's very unique um so getting into the
sort of
living in that bio region and um and
sort of being
enmeshed within that gift gave me a
perspective that was much bigger than
the the
one that um you know that um
my family was a but my family had did
this by design i guess
they brought us into that environment
and so when we were 11
uh years old we we went through the
the ceremony of finding your uh your
totem animal
and you know going through the
you know the various things that you you
go through so that was kind of my
introduction i guess to indigeneity
of australia from a white man's
perspective how do i
experience that well it's you know it's
it's not an easy journey but
um you know it's one i really wanted to
extend myself to truly try and
understand
um you know what does it mean from a
bioregional perspective and a
spiritual perspective to have that
relationship with the land
and the water and what took you on
because after you left your family farm
you did you study environmental science
because as far as i know you worked for
the permaculture research institute and
did quite a lot of work uh i studied
i i studied with the permaculture
research institute
that was in 2003 and i sort of started
getting deeply involved in permaculture
uh
you know when i was at university i got
involved in the environment collective
and you know we
got deeply involved in permaculture
growing food gardens and you know um you
know we would
um get involved in perma blitzing you
know backyards of many of our student
colleagues and friends
and uh you know that's where my interest
grew through studies
um now i i i
started getting involved on the teaching
side in year 2000
um i i sort of went into quite a few
different degrees actually like my first
degree
i went into was a banking and finance
which um i'm coming forward so i didn't
act
yeah yeah so i mean
because i i really understood economics
in a really good way and i got
all the straight a's and all everything
and i
could really grasp it but i also had a
creative side but
i ended up going into banking and
finance um
and thinking well that is the the best
way to try and influence things is
taking that approach
but i quickly got into it as an 18 year
old i thought wow this is really really
dry
and most of the folks in this course are
not my sort of folks
so i decided to to uh
after you know a year to defer that and
um
i then the next year i i started working
for nintendo
um and uh you know as a
ui ux user interface user experience
and sales guy you know to help them
product test
in australian market which is often used
as a product testing market for big tech
companies
before rolling out more globally and
regionally so
that was an interesting thing so i
started i started studying computer
science
and applied science um and then i really
got deeply into
that and design and uh software
development
but again i felt okay this is not really
matching
where i'm at so i finally said you know
well i should
i finally committed to a bachelor degree
of media and communications
and i started making short films about
environmental protest movement
um and um you know uh was deeply
involved in activism
and um you know that's where i really
started deepening
into permaculture so in youtube i
finished my degree in 2000
i went over to europe as a intern for
the zero emissions
research and initiative which was uh set
up by
crowley yeah i didn't know so
[Music]
yeah so that was like a six month
journey uh with them
you know there was a a three-story giant
bamboo pavilion was built
in germany on the expo in hanover when
when they brought them
yes yeah wonderful yeah actually now i
do remember that you did tell me when
you were here
yeah so so that was a great journey
and that's where i met a key mentor
george chan professor george chan
was a key mentor and so my job there was
to
essentially help gather all of the data
all of the intellectual capital and
knowledge that had been built
up uh in the network of zuri scientists
and
condensed it down into a cd-rom back in
a mini city room back in those days in
2000 like
city miniseries was cutting edge so we
we put it all down into a little
storybook um
and then we published some some
children's fables and stories about
ecology
you know how can i be the strongest tree
in the forest uh you know
illustrating interconnectivity um
i thought he did that later when he was
in cortiba the the series because i love
them
i read them to my daughter the six books
called
yeah so so so in 2000 we prototyped like
the very first one
so that was like a prototype of like the
first like
how can i be the strongest tree in the
forest was like
the first effort and when we put it uh
you know we just
took all illustrations worth put into
the city rom and like this is for
children we also got a lot of stuff
about integrated farming systems like
how do you
have super intensive polycultural
farming from you know
combining not just permaculture but
integrated farming systems from asia
which are
super productive you know uh and
professor george
chan he was the guy who you know he was
a head
environmental engineer of mauritius
actually who basically set up all of the
wastewater
and biogas systems and mauritius to kind
of you know ensure that they would
protect their
uh marine ecosystems uh and this was in
the 60s like super early on
um and uh so then
he sort of graduated on and on and after
he
he um he spent a lot of time in china
and southern china about
super intensive systems and he kind of
introduced me into
integrated farming systems which was i
guess you can say super intensive
polyculture
tropical style uh farming in southeast
asia and asia
east asia so that kind of gave me a
systems view on permaculture and then
we were learning industrial ecology from
people like emery lovins came and taught
us and
you know about first principles design
and we did some cool projects
with some german beer factories turning
uh
you know spent grain into bread and uh
growing mushrooms
oyster mushrooms to make them into
mushroom sausages um
you know this was all like when you said
emory lovins came and taught
us um is this within zeri or what
organization was us
at that point yes okay yeah that was
with siri yes
so so i was basically an intern slash
you know
deputy uh technical manager of azeri for
six months and so yeah set up their web
systems and their
education systems and and then as as a
result we got
like they would bring in teachers to
essentially that was part of the benefit
like you got an education
in systems to design for six months like
a living experience of systems design
uh with you know just the the best
thought leaders
on the planet at that time you know that
we could get access to so that was a
real
like deep dive and literally when i say
deep dive
uh we had we were piping in whale love
songs
from off the coast of south america
through a little microphone
that was designed based on the design on
the way
a whale's um ear is is structured
and so the way whale's ear is structured
so i learned biomimicry
there and um yeah these whale songs were
being piped in by a mobile phone in a
little buoy
and the microphone was designed exactly
like a whale's ear to listen to whale
songs and they were piping them 24 7
over to germany so that we could hear
whale love songs
and you know people would walk into our
our
gigantic three-story sort of bamboo
pavilion and say oh
and you know this this sound we'd say oh
it's whales making love you know the
coast of south america
you know um and it would
you know bring a laugh but it was just
so cool like in year 2000 that was
pretty breakthrough biomimicry
sort of explaining how does biomimicry
work like as a design science so that's
kind of led me into
deeper into and i edited george chan's
book um
called integrated farming and waste
management systems that was going to be
published by fao
but we needed to get a whole bunch of
new pictures
um for fao to publish it and it became a
little bit difficult so
it didn't happen but um you know that
kind of gave me the context for
permaculture
did my and i was teaching permaculture
with um
uh darren doherty and david holmgren
yeah down in victoria we would teach
together in bendigo
uh i used to sleep on darren's couch you
know
and you know we'd go and teach him today
so he darren became a mentor to me as
well
and you know then i did my pdc in 2003
uh with the permaculture research
institute to kind of make it official
and
learn a bit more about some of the large
scale earthworks uh and subtropical
system that um that jeff was doing in
australia
so yeah that's kind of i mean i went to
china um i worked on a
on an aussie um it was an aussie project
in china
in um the north northern china plains
and inner mongolia
it's just a massive uh you know massive
uh well what can i say it was like a
grasslands project
it was a step project you know it was a
massive scale and that was a five-year
project and i was there for one year of
that five years
uh building the educational information
training up
everyone from ministry staff right
through to farm extension offices in
villages so
my highlight there was building a lunar
calendar
for 40 million farmers that um
that had like monthly tips like this is
when you should do your compost
you know this is when you should be um
planting this when you should be
grafting walnut trees
you know apricots etc you know just and
we found out that if we didn't make it
super simple
and lunar calendar they were just like
going to use it for their
evening fire to cook their meals on like
in these villages so we
i sort of learned a lot from that how
did you integrate
local specificity and knowledge with all
this
these other techniques in the in that
calendar because i'm sure that
that some of the knowledge must have
been their own knowledge um
integrated exactly
it was yeah they were deeply deeply
knowledgeable
uh pockets of people who knew everything
there was to know
about um you know ecological agriculture
and so we did a lot of participatory
design uh
sessions across six major regions um it
was like 18.7
million hectares like the of coverage
like
just huge areas so we would have to
travel for days at a time
after in mongolia plateau you know past
the great wall
and then back down onto the uh the
plains and
you know that we would basically gather
this like participatory information
um it was mainly run by extremely
talented
uh women facilitators who would gather
up the women's
development association uh and they
gathered a lot of their information
from the women from the ground up about
you know you know
what do you do this week what do you do
next week and what do you do and what
are your techniques and
so there it was like they were basically
cultural anthropologists
uh employed by aussie um to kind of be
able to
understand all that local context
through deep interviewing
um so the first year was basically
participation management and then by the
time i got there
um it was then participatory management
let's plan together
about like what do you need next what do
you need next to
you know improve your water management
and uh how to
increase your productivity whilst
increasing you know
biodiversity soil fertility water
holding capacity because
we were there because there was a water
crisis all the rivers had been
completely extracted all the
shallow and medium aquifers were
completely depleted so all they had left
was deep deep ground water
and that's the very last bit of water
you're ever going to get
because it takes a long time to recharge
and the rivers are all dried up so what
are you going to do you
you have to make a really good water
budget and have to plan for that so we
were then going through participatory
water budgeting
at the level of the village and then
feeding that back up to the ministry to
like saying
you know you need to like set some water
budgets or you're gonna run out of water
and this was you know um you know like a
hundred million
farmers depending on that and it's like
the bread basket of
china so it was pretty serious um
uh you know and um the particular
province we were in
had some you know needed some uh
technical
uh training and you know hydro geology
and
modeling and other things um as well as
the
you know education we went out to the
villages and they would give like
you know a one-page brochure just
wall-to-wall text
zero images now most of the farmers were
illiterate and in the 70s so
it was just a mismatch and so it was
about trying to provide some context
about
um capacity building and was this
prior or after you developed this um
aqua filter system
to for cleaning waste water yeah
so i got the inspiration for um
developing the aqua biofilter the
floating wetland system
from george chan um in 2000 at ziri
uh so that was uh so george
when i was you know george was training
as you know
um quite intensively in integrated
farming systems and
systems designed more broadly and he
showed us
he said you know we had a problem in our
fish ponds that there was just too much
nutrient
in there and so he said we started
growing rice on top of the fish ponds to
take up the nutrient and clean the water
i was like that's so cool um but it was
on like very like rough material so they
were doing it with bamboos but then the
bamboos would
degrade very quickly and you're building
new ones and neurons every year
uh then they there were experiments with
polystyrene and
which of course it was very
unsustainable material so
i sort of started coming at it from from
a design science perspective how can we
improve this system
and more broadly create an ecological
management tool that
purifies water heals waterways and lakes
and restores them to help so
so that's kind of how i came to develop
the aqua biofilter um
and so so when i got back to australia i
started developing prototypes of it
and kept in touch with george and some
of the other broader network
and then um you know got some funding
from the australian government
to do some trials and then so in 2004
when i was actually
in china that's when we got involved
with the broader network
with a large trial where we
had some input as aqua biofilter and got
involved a little bit in some projects
there which were
a pretty massive scale um
and it was the largest aquaponics system
in the world was it
like i read something yeah i think it
was at that at that
time it was it was it was it was massive
it was acres and acres
of floating wetlands um so
yeah it was it was the biggest of that
time
i mean i know that you you know the work
of john todd who was my second
phd supervisor because he also did some
um floating
wetland systems in in china um
around that time or maybe even before
that but have you come across
by matrix water in scotland um which is
a sort of like my friend
and his father-in-law michael shaw um
michael shaw used to work with john todd
and they then started biomatrix in
in scotland and they're doing wonderful
work in urban regeneration using
floating wetlands and
active edge technology and um
you come across them yeah actually i
think
i think actually yes um definitely and i
remember seeing a post from that you
shared and
um and actually maybe we did chat about
this a couple years ago
i think you might have mentioned it then
um but that was quite a while ago but i
think
yes definitely i'm gonna admire what
they've done like
it's so cool uh you know restoring the
waterways
um so i think we're we're kind of like a
similar version of biometrics but you
know being very focused on australia
and in asia um and a bit on the us
um but uh you know i is that company
yeah
so yeah yeah the company's still around
and it's
you know it's still got some operations
in australia um
but um what what is it called because i
found one that was called
eco plan um that was time yeah so
so that was a consulting uh company you
know um
that uh i was uh very involved with for
you know a number of years um as an
environmental consult planning
consultant
this was sort of back from that time of
2005 when i got back to australia
um you know got quite worked as an
environmental planning consultant
um mainly for other big consulting firms
that would have
good contracts with the government to
essentially do environmental impact
assessments
uh habitat protection habitat surveys um
and uh yeah is that around the same time
where you worked for the public
authority and did that integrated
building design
um and developed the green building
council
um yeah that was in uh that was in two
that was in 2009 uh
that uh that project with the green
building so i sort of got quite a lot
involved in environmental consulting and
i was doing aqua biofilter on the side
um you know when projects and
opportunities would come up would do
that
and i was working um so yeah
got involved with melbourne water for uh
two years um
you know doing some different roles but
mainly strategic planning
around how do you basically restore
entire catchments you know
their their catchment size is 1.3
million hectares
uh you know drinking water for five six
million people
uh and so we had to
essentially develop a water quality
model that would improve the health of
the
all of the rivers you know um um
oh apologies i think i just dropped off
there so someone tried to call me
um so uh yeah so so we
we so i had a job there um in 2007
and uh 2008 which was kind of the
culmination of my consulting kind of
career and environment and uh we
developed a thing called the decision
support system which was essentially
a metrics tool that allowed you to make
informed decisions about where you
should
invest in your catchment you know
where's the high biodiversity areas
where's the most pristine waterways
and where do you have the most biosignal
across your catchments
and essentially model that which was not
too dissimilar to what i've been doing
in china with aussie
and then sort of but making it very
contextual for the bayer region of
melbourne's
water um and you know really hone in on
you know what are the decision metrics
that power your investment
prioritization
so we had a budget of essentially 300
million that we
um built up for the better bays and
waterways
program that the decision support system
informed so that was like a five-year
plan
that we set up for melbourne water
called beta-based waterways
and that was in partnership with epa
victoria um and melbourne water
so we we basically developed very
complex water quality model for the
region
and i developed i know i think it was 20
or 30 scenarios to 2030 of
you know what are all the worst things
that could possibly happen to destroy
your water supply
you know you could have fires you could
have pandemics you could have all sorts
of things
happen and what can you do this is back
in 2017
to invest so that you can avoid all of
those down
side scenarios so that was my job to
envision the worst and then plan for
that
and then try and do the best and
allocate so it ended up allocating about
300 million
um to going into paying farmers and land
managers to
uh essentially provide ecosystem you
know services
uh essentially to melbourne water and
melbourne water's first stakeholder
is the environment the second
stakeholder is
water consumers who need to drink pure
water and so the idea is if you if the
environment is your first stakeholder
then you're going to have
pure uh drinking water and
so your second class stakeholder this is
back then in the waterways group that i
was part of
that's that means you're going to be
getting the most pure quality water
possible to those people with the least
amount of treatment
uh the least amount of pollution in
there so
that was kind of a real pleasure and it
rolled into this thing called eco
markets
which the department of sustainability
environment then sort of we
input a lot of what we've been doing at
melbourne water into that model
um to kind of power the decision metrics
to power the invest public investment
program
um yeah about 300 million and it's still
going today and it's just
even more now i don't know how many
hundreds of millions it's
it's just grown and grown how integrated
was that work at the time because it
sounds like it's a massive bio-regional
um project that that looks at water
management at the
bioregional scale with this link between
city and region like melbourne and its
region um but was it was it also
integrated with all the other energy
water transfer
energy transport and building um because
you you also worked on some some kind of
design for a urban neighborhood or what
what project you developed yeah yeah
oh the big eco neighborhood that was
yeah that was uh
yeah that was kind of when i was working
on my sort of environmental planning and
consulting and yeah we were building
permaculture gardens as well on the side
um i got involved with a local group
called big eco neighborhood
um where darren darwin you know we
actually taught some permaculture design
courses with
john champagne who's based there in
bieger
uh region by region um and we
you know i was living there at the time
and uh
uh for a couple of years and it's just
not far from the beautiful wild area i
described of our farm
it's just not far from there um where i
grew up so i
kind of returned there to live for a few
years and uh
you know just had a beautiful
reconnection with that area um and the
big eco neighborhood project came about
because
you know a whole bunch of local people
came together and said well
you know we're all living on separate
blocks and we're all coming into town
and buying at our bulk
whole foods organic shop and you know
why don't we actually
you know there's a lot of environmental
activism to save some of the ogre forest
you know that was um still left
and um you know we got together and said
why don't we actually form an eco
neighborhood together
buy some land build a community house
and
make it affordable housing and you know
let's do this so
we've sort of found a block of land
right on the edge of town
um uh and yeah we bought it for 500 000
as a non-profit incorporated association
which gives absolutely zero investor
protection so this meant everyone
actually
had to trust each other with that sort
of sum of money
and that you were gonna everyone's gonna
do the right thing um
and and yeah it worked amazingly you
know it was just a beautiful experience
and i got involved
in the design of the from the very
beginning through to um
implementation and um yeah it's a
thriving neighborhood now of uh
i think it's about 23 or 24 houses um
um or even more because uh one-third of
the property was sold to a co-housing
co-op uh and so sort of uh duplexes were
built so sold off some land to them they
then built seven
duplexes i think which is um pegged to
below market rate and permaculture
gardens are there and
the river flows through this we did
wetlands restoration project and
natural swimming pool uh using aqua
biofilter kind of
technologies and yeah that was a great
you know community
experience of building community it's
really thriving
um today um and yeah
it's great later when you work for
public authority didn't you take the
this kind of integrated systems designed
to i seem to remember something that i
found was called the local government
urban regeneration project
um uh yes so yeah so
so after i left melbourne water um i
got asked basically this municipal
government approached me and said look
we like the work you've been doing about
water why you come work for us
we're just about to launch a super
exciting you know uh green precinct
project
um you know which is basically going to
build the local community hub
you know that is going to have 1 million
visitors a year you know that needs to
be cutting edge sustainability
green uh you know total water
sustainability total
energy sustainability so yeah i got
involved with that for two years as a
strategic sustainably engineer and
planner and
uh you know dive really deep and that
was part of the group called the major
projects unit
which basically it was a contractor to
all other
municipal governments to build whatever
they needed you know you need a building
will build you need a road and build it
you know just
it was though too backward municipal
governments in australia could still
build things
like themselves that was um kind of
which is sad that they don't now but um
this is kind of the last one
um so so you know so
what we did was we um built uh
my role was to help essentially create
the first uh green star public green
building
in australia so that was a very great
job to be tasked with
and um you know it was a 40 million
building and i
my job was saying okay well where's the
budget for green and sustainability and
they said well we really don't have one
and they said your job is to go find the
mice so that was that's what i had to do
so um so we started writing a lot of
grants
started meeting a lot of government
people and industry people and and
got involved with the green building
council and said look we could be
the very first public green building in
australia
and no rating system exists for that yet
so the green building council australia
said look it doesn't exist yet if you
want to
have a green public building you have to
create the tool so we said
well i'm up for a challenge you know
let's create the public building tool
for the greenville and council australia
with our first
municipal kind of hub which is a
community hub building essentially it
houses
about 30 different community
organizations it's a regional library
it has a
children's education area community
health area it has a
pottery studio a kiln an art gallery
it's also a satellite
campus for a bachelor of applied science
in
green architecture it's got real-time
readouts of your energy usage your water
usage and um
i commissioned a study to see could we
get our
power from biogas and so there was a a
large
sort of shopping mall not far away that
had six tons
a week of you know green and food waste
that was just going straight to landfill
and so we commissioned a study to see
well how much energy could we get
from that you know what is now food
waste and we could
put a biodigester in the basement of
this building turn into biogas and
power you know the buildings so we did a
full-on feasibility study
uh and yeah it showed we could power at
least 240 kilowatts like permanently 24
uh you know with biogas um
and it was you know we were on the verge
of
doing it but um you know unfortunately
at that time
you know there was well the gas prices
were extremely
uh low uh compared to biogas and there
was
there was no incentive to switch to
biogas there was no
regenerative economic incentive to say
you know
you're doing something good for the
environment and you're producing energy
and so the economics couldn't stack up
and for me
there was another realization that you
need to work at
a policy level you need to work at
systemic financial
system level uh you need to work with
communities
um and that was kind of another lesson
that and i saw at melbourne water how
we'd make it
work like public private partnership for
funding models
where your first state quarter was the
environment it kind of i thought okay
well
energy and green buildings is not quite
there yet but
it gave me ideas which fed into kind of
what would land
earth bank um fighting regenerative
economic incentive models
and kind of mainstreaming into the
financial system so
before yeah that was a cool fun project
before we get to earth bank
i just really want to hit all this
because it's it's quite
unique like um you've really like for
what you set out to do with earth bank
um your trajectory has given you
all the right background to really
understand down to the detail
the kind of things that earth bank is
now exploring how to
finance those activities at scale
so so you really that done you a long
learning journey that
and it seems like you're really bringing
all the elements together but before
before we go to earth bank
on one more chapter um which is your
work with alan savory
on um landscape regeneration and
actually
the work with with the um core forum in
in switzerland um tell us a little bit
more
yes yes yes for sure um just
to recap on that green building it did
get built and it's got its
own island mode fully self-sufficient
powered
you know building of like 12 000 square
meters so it
we actually got it up and running and um
it's it's in operation but okay
switching to alan savory
to that building like how would i find
the link yeah it's called
it's called mc squared um and
it's in melbourne uh australia um
so yeah we um i'll send you a link on
that so that you can
yeah great yeah mcsquared like this
so yeah uh alan savory uh and i met
in uh switzerland at the co forum
um which is now was called the
co-dialogue
for land and security uh which was
trying to bring together you know how do
you get more
peace development through better
regenerative
uh sort of landed water management
practices and policies
particularly with a focus on the arid
dry lands um
a lot of folks come to switzerland each
year whether from
you know from war-torn regions across
you know african middle east
particularly to try and
work things out and find out what could
we do
to kind of prevent conflict how can we
reconcile from conflict
uh and so there's a lot of peace circle
work goes on there to
essentially facilitate healing um
reconciliation
um which also in fact after world war ii
also happened
their reconciliation um so that um
europe could start to rebuild so it's
got a bit of a profound history
um and so yeah that was
that was an interesting journey there
for over the last 10 years i've been
involved
with the conference there um i was a
co-scholar which
was basically a one month piece building
uh
sort of course uh which is a university
credit course
um and i started that i think was 2008
or 2007 and
um then got involved in getting the ngo
accredited with the unf triple c to
start attending cops
and then that grew into going to unccd
cops so with the un
convention to combat um desertification
uh and through that journey with a
friend martin frick who's um
done a lot in the climate and also food
and agriculture organizations
uh you know really started getting co
you know he brought on board the
executive director of the unccd
to co-found this uh
series of conferences the co-dialogue
and land of security and that's where
alan came into the picture we brought
all the sort of thought leaders of
regenerative agriculture together and
you indeed were invited i remember um
um and but yourself and darren does some
other friends couldn't quite make it for
you know various reasons
as an ngo there wasn't um you know it's
always difficult
um but uh you know so we brought
together a lot of people
i invited the permaculture research
institute team along as well they met
john liu john who made lots of films
about them john lew made some
like the best films out there on
regeneration in terms of inspiring
you know huge audience like so so we all
got together rattan lal
who just won the um the award this week
for his great work on soils he was there
and you
so we all got together and said we
should write a book uh you know to bring
all this knowledge together
uh into one kind of source of of truth
about this is how you can restore
landscapes
at scale uh and this can contribute to a
more peaceful world it can contribute to
uh a more abundant world um and so
you know we yeah so a good friend of
mine jennifer helgeson
she's a phd from london school of
economics she did her
phd and developed an app on micro
insurance
farmers in uganda so she was like how
can you help
protect the most vulnerable
farmers in the world from climate risk
you know
and destruction of your crops and she
pioneered a lot of that
and so generally you know she's now
chief climate economist
at earth bank um uh she you know so
we worked together on this book for
several years alan savory and i
worked on a chapter called regenerating
agriculture to sustain civilization
and so alan and i over a period of about
a year
would send you know we would write our
our
our chapter together and ping ideas off
each other and
sort of you know how do we try to bring
together the different threads of you
know there's
holistic management uh there was threads
of keyline
uh you know scale of permanence uh
permaculture
um and other broader strategic meta
frameworks that were out there how do we
converge them
into something that is legible for the
average person
but also can be used in an academic
context to try and make sense of all
these different threads
you know so the book called land
restoration was published in 2016
by elsivia and is now used by many
universities and colleges around the
world to teach
uh agriculture and agronomy students all
around the world
and jen jennifer did something amazing
she negotiated with elsivia to say
well look this should be free for the
developing world
you know you can't you know this this is
a 120 book
you know which someone you know in in
usa europe might be able to afford but
you know we need to get this knowledge
out there so she
really bargained hard with um i'll save
you and i mean we essentially gave all
of our time for free
you know it's for the good of you know
we need to get this information all
together in one place it's 500
and something pages like long it's
massive
um so i wrote two chapters in the book
uh retired lyle
john liu uh you know lots of great
contributors
um and uh you know what it ended up
doing is now
it's used it's it's a it's given freely
this as a textbook for the developing
world to
universities colleges everywhere so that
was kind of how
alan and i sort of worked together on
that chapter and sort of brought it
together as a
that was part of the economic strain was
um you know
the economics of uh you know land
restoration
um particularly it was like trying to
get to a meta scale to sort of say well
how do you avoid civilizational collapse
you know how do you do that and what are
the first principles that you need
to look at and observe and
and and where possible to adopt in a
really holistic context
and so we you know we answer that
question in a nutshell like
um do we have flowers
um where do you think would
people should start that journey of of
um
seriously thinking about how to reinvent
agriculture
from the ground up yes
yes it's um you know the chapter was
called regenerating
agriculture to sustain civilization and
i think that encapsulates
quite a few of the truths that you know
unless
we truly regenerate agriculture from the
soil
up um you know no amount of
green energy no amount of
um you know uh switch from fossil fuels
is going to save us from civilizational
collapse
um and uh i think the data proves that
i mean we could we could even argue
whether we've ever had
a civilization worthy its name that was
truly civil
um with regard to the rest of life
um now there are some people who say
that the whole project of
a civilization which is often conceived
of as some sort of
one-size-fits-all global or very large
entity um is maybe making concept
because
most of the previous civilizations that
were referred to
were too big not to fail and maybe maybe
that's the case for ours
but but i think when we use the word
civilization we're talking about
something else
we're talking about a diverse
network of regenerative cultures
carefully adapted to their bio regions
that still hold the benefit of global
awareness and knowledge exchange
in a way that they are in solidarity
with each other so it's a kind of
nested scaling civilization that that
is uniquely expressed out of place in
each
location um would you would you would
you
sign on the doc i would concur
my friend that that is uh
for sure the case i i sense that like
i mean it's it's really remarkable the
the journey that you we've just outlined
with everything that you've already been
involved in but but
i think the most remarkable step um is
still to come which is that that
you you then realize that the highest
leverage point like
in the degenerative system that is
driving the degeneration
at the fastest pace that it is
still happening right now is our
dysfunctional economic system
and the way that we handle finance work
with
banks and um and
how this insidious growth imperative
that is built
into an economic system that is is
blinded
to externalities because it only
measures everything in
gdp um is really at the heart
of the problem and and so i believe
that's when you started to work on
on um all these new technologies that
this is where we're leaving my comfort
zone i'm a little bit
um of a self-professed luddite and and
having difficulties with all that
techy crypto stuff but um
you developed something called liquid
tokens and and really looked deeply into
how can we use these technologies for
good
and and then realize that really what's
needed is a new back
um so out of that developed what is now
called earth bank so
tell us how that journey started
yeah yeah this is the transition to this
was a
interesting journey that that kind of i
guess
you know really started you know back in
my days at melbourne water where we
you know we developed this kind of
strategic plan for
a buyer region and a city-state and you
know
worked out a big budget of how do you
you know pay
uh land holders and farmers for
ecosystem services and that kind of
always stuck in my memory that
you know well couldn't all governments
be
as wise as that um you know and develop
policies that um that have environment
as your first stakeholder if you're
providing drinking water
and i thought yeah having worked in a
lot of
different sort of government contexts
around the world felt that this is going
to be very hard
to achieve you know this this level of
complex
uh coordination and coherence i think i
got you know the more i got you know
with the green buildings and raising a
lot of money
for sustainability initiatives and then
renewable energy
i was based in southeast asia for three
years you know quite involved in
in renewable energy policy and renewable
energy projects and
some very large scale and got involved
in renewable energy project finance
uh and you know at that time you know
um and i got involved in funds
management uh as well that
you know which was more of a
conventional fund uh but would strive
where possible to
invest in in green real estate after
having the green real estate experience
i
thought okay this is a not only is it
really imperative for the planet that we
that we uh
transition to green real estate it's
actually a business opportunity that
people can
you know benefit if you can benefit the
local community from having better
facilities um better thermal comfort um
you know we could leverage capital into
that and that could be a good business
to be in
um so i sort of got involved in funds
management
uh you know green real estate
development
project finance and i got involved in
the public capital markets as well
in some some some ipos
on the australian securities exchange
some was an ag tech company
another was a fintech company and
over time i started um figuring out
that you know the capital markets being
so hyper liquid
and uh having you know the volume of
money that goes
through uh public equities markets is
just massive
and so i started looking at what i'm
doing on the fund management side
and looking at project finance and then
looking at the public equities markets
and i was seeing all the ace
symmetries and where the gaps were where
there's bottlenecks
and then sort of mapping that onto my
history in
regenerative and economic sort of
environmental developments to say well
where could these map you know
coherently to provide some new
architecture
um to be able to facilitate the
transition and
flow of billions of dollars or even
trillions of dollars that the world
needs
into the these very specific activities
of regeneration at scale
um and it led me to the conclusion that
ultimately you need to retool the
financial system you need to retool
capital and repurpose and provide
purpose
and so when i came across blockchain and
back to my computer science days i
thought well blockchain is very
interesting
you could program money
to achieve certain policy outcomes
now if your policy is regeneration uh
at scale you know drawing down carbon
providing abundant healthy food
uh restoring fertility of soil what are
the principles
um that you can code into a currency to
then achieve those goals
what are the incentives you could create
to facilitate that
um whether at policy level whether at
bank level
whether a local buyer regional uh mutual
uh credits and mutual economic transfer
systems
um you know like i've experimented with
local currency in 2003 through
2006 and seven on the big eco
neighborhood project if you were a local
contractor like you're a builder a
concrete and an electrician
you could essentially get you could
essentially use your local economic
um transfer currency let's in
as a down payment uh on a block and you
could
essentially use local currency to buy
the property that and you'd been helping
out build it out
so from a local currency perspective and
then blockchain comes along
like okay this is really interesting you
know programmable money
uh that has a purpose and a goal whereas
right now i think we would agree that
we yeah that capital is like this
self-replicating
thing that replicates without context to
local
context biodiversity people culture all
the things that we really value and hold
dear to our heart
capital is just a self-replicating thing
like the self-replicating um
you know paper clip experiment just keep
replicating and growing
without context to you know the things
we hold dearest
and i think if we could provide that
context
to money and infuse you know decision
metrics to say well
why don't we make money smart and
capital smart
true and having worked in that policy
arena of writing
helping write policy and programs that
are scalable i thought
there needs to be a way to bring that
knowledge
base into code base um and try
to work backwards because knowing that
governments you know the scale that we
need to move
and the scale and fast and speed that
governments move at
uh and also having worked at that local
community level seeing how long it takes
to build that cultural
glue to work together and trust and
build that up
it kind of felt to me well there
definitely needs to be a systemic
level initiative that is bringing that
knowledge base into a new code base and
a new architecture financial command
for financial systems and so my approach
to that was liquid token to say well
if we can tokenize an asset and make it
liquid
uh and have an own internal marketplace
which sets the price at a fair price
so it's not making it's not increasing
volatility
it's increasing liquidity but without
increasing volatility
uh i.e it's not um rent-seeking or
extractive on
the underlying which is uh land people
communities
and so i started to think well if you
can do that
just so i'm but i understand this
correctly um liquidizing an asset means
that if
if it's there's a value towards let's
say a building or
even a property um and
you issue tokens that liquid tokens that
are
backed by that asset
therefore create liquidity
um and
how do you protect the asset against
like if something fails like would i
would would a
token holder ever come back and and say
um
i want a piece of that asset or i own
that asset because
most of the liquid tokens related to
that asset
yeah so so it brings in a layer of
governance
uh that's important to say you know if
this happens then what
you know what if then this happens and
then you sort of create a logic that
says well
you know if if um you know for example a
green building
is a good example investments in green
buildings you know generally you have a
minimum
time horizon of at least 10 years
you know as an investor you're going to
invest in that
knowing it's going to take a certain
amount of time to recover the money
you've put into it
okay to break even then
once you've broken even you're like okay
well
hopefully i can now get paid for the
work i've done um
so then okay there's a period of getting
paid um
your income and then you're sort of at a
point where okay
[Music]
now do i sell this asset and then move
on to the next one
and so um the thing is
you know if you want to encourage uh at
scale
investment into green buildings like
like i can say from experience like i
know some of the biggest green building
funds in australia and they're not that
big
you know and so i look at well what are
some of the constraints
and why is that um and one of the issues
is
is liquidity you know real estate is a
long-term
um industry but it's there's so much
credit and liquidity from banks that is
all geared towards totally unsustainable
development
and if you want to do something
sustainable and something different
the bank's like well i don't know if we
want to give you a loan for that i don't
know if
we want to give you mortgages to do a
community garden on the roof
and the whole thing green and you know
super insulated why can't you just do
what everyone else does
and so banks you know until very
recently were very
um not supportive of green building
developments
now they're all over it because you know
esg
and reporting and they have to you know
so much more active activist
shareholders
bringing scrutiny to their activities so
um
you know back then it was like well how
do you get more uh cash flowing in
but you can increase the the total
volume of money coming into this segment
and so one thesis is that one of the
ways you do that
is by creating funds that are actually
liquid
where people can easily come in and out
of the fund
now traditionally when you're asked to
come into a fund as an investor you
you say well okay once you come into
this fund your money is locked up for 10
years
and you don't get your money back so for
quite a lot of people and particularly
regular folks that's a very strong
disincentive to invest
in green buildings and so my perspective
was well if we could
reduce that disincentive and and make an
incentive
to invest in green building funds then
more money is going to flow into the
sector and therefore there's going to be
more green building developments
um so so liquidity optionality
is a really good thing in that case now
one of the ways to protect
the against volatility is where you have
an internal market so what we did with
liquid token we built it essentially as
a
fund management tool um you know for
fund managers to use
um so you could so basically what liquid
token
software as a product can do is
essentially a fund manager can say yep i
want to use liquid token to run my fund
and so liquid token gets set up it
tokenizes a fund
or it just moves it onto the blockchain
it doesn't necessarily have to be
tokenized
uh amazon or blockchain is a
basically to manage the cap table of
equity holders in a fund
or unit holders in a fund and then what
we do is we facilitate that those
uh shareholders can actually find each
other
in a peer-to-peer manner and actually
sell and buy
between themselves so they don't have to
go back to the fund manager and say i
want my money back and the fund manager
says
sorry no can do whereas what we're doing
is empowering
the fund investors to find each other on
the platform
within the sort of liquid token
environment and essentially
buy and sell between each other and say
you know one investor might like i'd
like to increase my holding in this
uh project one say i want to decrease my
holding the price is stable and is set
by the fund manager
so you're not increasing volatility but
you are increasing liquidity
so that people can come in and out
without fear of
all your money being locked up for 10
years so we're trying to in that sense
democratize access
also to investing in green
infrastructure renewable energy because
liquid is a separate company that's
running that's offering this service and
and you're still involved with it but
but then you you move on to
earth bank afterwards so liquid token is
a software
that was developed and um and so
yeah so liquid token is not a a company
uh
it's it's a software product yeah so
so uh so we so we've absorbed some of
liquid token
software capabilities into earth bank
in terms of being able to offer fund
fund management software services
and also that extends to green digital
banking
services uh software services as well so
we've sort of rolled some of the
software capabilities that we've
built up in liquid token into earth bank
in terms of the digital
technology capability okay so if
somebody buys that software to use it
um then they they deal with earth bank
yeah yeah yeah that's that's right yeah
yeah i mean so
liquid yeah earth bank yeah and how it
evolved
and because on the website it also
mentions that you've actually been
involved in uh we just read it out our
digital banking platform is part of the
central bank
blockchain fintech sandbox to issue new
digital
financial product and archive
and archives the horizon 2020 goals um
of preventing runaway climate change so
you have you actually worked on
the the policy development behind the
new european funding
um on horizon like beyond horizon 2020
or
well i don't quite understand that
no so so yeah
okay so yes i'll explain uh
so we uh so earth bank got accepted into
the european institute of innovation and
technology's
uh incubator and accelerator program
and uh so which includes some venture
backing
some investment um and what
what uh eit the
the sort of stream that earth bank
fell into uh into in in
eit which uh neit is a co-architect of
horizon 2020 and the greener deal
uh of europe uh which was i know it's a
trillion euro
close to that um and now with the green
recovery is like 1.75 trillion
so so so the people who gave us venture
backing
to develop decision metrics for climate
finance
they're the ones who also that same body
that
invested in us they're the same body
that developed
you know helped co-architect uh the
green uh
new deal so and there was there's a
there's a
a quite well-known economist from italy
um
who has kind of helped architect this
vision for europe of
you know how do you invest in innovation
uh and how does the state get involved
in helping see
the funding of innovation very much like
what has happened in the us you know
they've got a very
strong set of sort of investment
programs
in technology startups but a lot of that
is tied
to defense activity now in europe the
european institute for innovation
and technology has got nothing to do
with defense
it's it's looking at defense of the
planet from a climate perspective
public health you know kind of key
priority areas for europe
uh that that um you know needs massive
investment
um and so horizon 2020 was a big bucket
of money
that has gone into startups like ours to
develop uh
the stream that coheres with european
policy
um of you know being climate neutral
carbon neutral by 2050 and so where
earth bank fits into that
sort of meta strategic design is that
you know we i
i personally and others on our team have
a great history uh like
now chief climate economist and others
have a great history and our data
scientists
uh have a great history of developing
decision metrics tools
to drive investment into ecosystem
restoration at scale
uh and power new financial products like
micro insurance for farmers
um and so we got some venture backing to
do that because
if you're going to roll out a green new
deal you better invest in the right
things otherwise you could be throwing a
trillion euros down
oops you know the proverbial so i think
that's kind of
a key consideration yeah and i mean
because that that's one of the like in
the discourse
in social media and the public sphere at
the moment there are a lot of voices
that are very critical about the the
green new deal
technological right response to um both
the pandemic and
and the climate crisis but i i often
find that
um it's a little bit disheartening
because i really know a lot of people
that are in that area
doing good work with with who are
very well intentioned and while
i i would say that of course all these
technological and
innovation and technology changes are
only part of the transformation that
we're now
um in front of and have to achieve
relatively quickly
but it's still setting the conditions
for real transformative societal change
to happen
if we invest in all these technologies
um
so in developing green green bank like
are you based getting european funding
to to to launch this are you based in
europe
as a company or where where are you
registered
yeah so so earth bank uh there's there's
um we have some uh so there's a presence
in sweden
uh there's a presence in the uk and
there's also a presence in usa
uh and so we need to take a bit of a
global approach to this
to you know try and be truly systemic um
and uh yeah so it's been great getting
support
uh in europe and the nordics for what
earth bank is doing the nordics are
quite strong on environmental analytics
as well and fintech
uh so it's been good uh getting support
there and uh you know
we we think that europe is the right
place to start
because of the um the policy map
um that is already
laid out and agreed to and funded
and so you know it makes sense to build
the financial architecture to help that
transition of transitioning billions of
dollars
into the right area with our decision
metrics
so we we were part of a central bank uh
blockchain and fintech uh program uh
specifically for fintechs that had
blockchain capabilities and technologies
and were fintechs it just so happens we
were the first climate
of fintech to be accepted into that
program so
we we were kind of unique in that sense
that getting to work with a central bank
is quite special it's a little bit
unique
you don't really tend to get access like
that um usually
so we were lucky you know i think uh
there was only a very a handful of
companies chosen to go into the program
and you know we were we were there so
that sort of consisted of six months
this is european one called
this is this is it's it's a it's a
national central bank that is supervised
by the european central bank
um and they're very strong on blockchain
and they're very
they're also the biggest issuer of
digital banking licenses in europe
uh so you know the biggest digital banks
you think of like revolut
you know 10 million plus users they're
licensed by this
uh central bank uh google pay is less
you know the big
so they're you know they license the big
digital uh banking
uh platforms but uh and wallets sort of
systems out there
um so that's good for us in terms of
being able to access
um a license that can cover all of
europe instantly
so as a startup that sort of thing is
you know quite helpful
uh and we're going through the process
now of of um
of of the digital licensing process
so yeah so now we're kind of in a really
good place
uh where we've put in the hard work and
we're kind of battle tested
you know we the central bank and
technology partners
actually assessed our technology to see
could we
actually issue accounts on this
blockchain could we
issue you know green bonds green funds
and then
have people uh invest in those
funds you know this was in a test
environment in the central bank test
environment
where we would test all the
functionalities of you know
uh issuing a green digital bond someone
buying it someone selling it and then
also having a
secondary market inside of earth bank to
trade
whether it's green bonds or esg
investments or bundled up
regenerative assets um so yeah we kind
of went through that
six-month process of you know working
weekly with the central bank
supervisors and technology experts and
uh third-party providers of technology
uh
and yeah it was a great experience that
kind of positions earth bank to
you know be a platform that can actually
issue green
financial instruments that can help
accelerate you know massive carbon
drawdown
not just in the europe region but more
broadly
you know that achieving uh carbon
neutral by 2050 you know that's
that's pretty difficult when your supply
chains extend globally
and so you really need to look at the
global perspective
um you know if you want to achieve that
scale of change quickly
so yeah so we're well positioned if if
you
got a chance to to write the perfect
future for
um earth bank over the next 10 years
um how would you see it develop and and
uh
what would you see as the main impacts
and benefits
from its success
yeah yeah well
the ideal future state that i would like
to
uh be in is a future where
you know earth bank has managed to
achieve a systemic
level kind of of regenerative impact
and by that i mean you know drawing down
enough carbon to buy the planet
you know time to decarbonize its economy
and
go regenerative um you know it looks
more like deep social equity
at local level um
where farmers are paid a fair price for
their what they're doing and incentivize
to restore soils
uh where renewable energy that is
not kind of contaminated by dirty supply
chains uh you know is truly
more sustainable um and you have 24 7
renewables not sort of standby
coal and gas power there to
you know in equal measure to renewable
energy system because that's not
sustainable
so you you know it would look like a
very different world
in 2030 and being the decade of
ecosystem restoration
this is the really big area for us is
protecting
those key critical biodiversity and
habitat periods
that contain the most biodiversity in
the world and they're also
the most climate vulnerable people in
the world those areas would be protected
the people would be paid to care for
those ecosystems
because those ecosystems i mean 50
percent of the world's
land is actually under indigenous
management
and there's right now there's no way to
connect the trillions of dollars being
printed
by central banks there's no mechanism
right now to actually
finally get that money to end up in
their pockets
so that they're able to take care of the
last remaining old growth forest or the
last remaining tiger of the sunderbans
mangroves you know the largest
blue carbon storage of mangroves on the
planet
um and so that's why we're working
directly in the sunda buns in india we
just planted 30 000 trees
as part of building a green wall to
protect the local community from
hurricane driven storm surges
is it's the last bastion of the swamp
tiger that lives there
and unless you can kind of protect your
blue carbon storage of mangroves
unless you can protect the key areas of
the amazon
um you know runaway climate change is
is an absolute certainty so we have to
protect what we've got
and we have to regenerate what has been
degenerated
so to me it's a patchwork
of work that has shifted the balance
that we've avoided runaway climate
change
and we're starting to actually move co2
ppm
backwards which people say is impossible
right now
but if you look at what agricultural
soils and marginal
soils have got you know you could draw
down
gigaton scales you know and our friends
at the unccd the
u.n convention for combat
desertification have done the math and
said look if you spent 300 billion
dollars
on this particular area of marginal
grasslands that have been degraded
just that activity alone and a few other
things
you know you can buy the planet 15 25
years to decarbonize
and so one one of them did i always find
really important as a piece of um like
to to remind people of
is that as we talk about
biosequestration and carbon drawdown
um into into biomass and into our new
material culture that is more
biomaterials based um i mean you can
lock
through there's already a lot of
skyscrapers being built with
with wood structures inside of bamboo
structures inside so you can lock
carbon into the built environment for
quite a long time
200 300 years even but the carbon cycle
in the biological carbon cycle is still
a relatively short-lived cycle not
necessarily from a human
lifetime perspective um it's a few human
lifetimes but
but from a life perspective um the
long range perspective it's only 300 250
300 years something like that
um so to not hit
a ceiling in this i agree with you that
it is
possible and we have an opportunity
to still come back to 250 parts per
million to actually
get to a pre-industrial level of co2 in
the atmosphere
but um it needs also
the transfer from biological sequestered
carbon
into geological sequestration and there
are some
bios mechanisms that can do that i mean
coral reefs and um sea grass
and um some
fungal symbiotic relationships between
certain trees
can actually mineral mineralize um
biological carbon and therefore take it
into the geological
cycle which is 10 000 years and and
then we're in the game and we're good
absolutely this is a very important
point you've
you've um crystallized that
that we need to get it into the
geological time scale
uh and so humic carbon uh
and and calciferous sort of calcium
carbonates
um so you know when you start to get
into the
humic carbon formation and you start to
get
um calcium carbonate formation
and you start to get into that
geological time scale that's where we
need to get 100
and mangroves are very very key
to that if you can't protect your
mangroves and if you don't restore
mangroves and so we've got this thing we
call it the mangrove moon shot
you know if you planted 20 billion
mangroves right which is totally doable
based on assessment by the iucn which is
also a partner in
the conference the co conference each
year
is that you know you can plan 20 billion
now what happens is you start restoring
the mangroves and i think you know this
very well and this is for your viewers
to say
that you know as as the mangroves
restore then they're starting to filter
a lot of sediment
and then those uh you know seagrasses
are starting to recover
and then the seagrasses together with
the mangroves
is just this carbon sequestration like
swim power
and the fish hatcheries that replenish
the fisheries
and the fisheries when they bounce back
enable the whales to
increase in in numbers and the whales
have always been
the nutrient pump in the ocean um
bringing
nutrients back from deep ocean
foraging to the surface of the ocean to
increase by productivity in the surface
oceans
which is actually another carbon
drawdown mechanism so you you create a
positive kind of green swan positive
feedback chain and and suddenly
you're you're regenerating those systems
starting with mangroves and starting
with seagrasses
is definitely um also where i would put
my bit
before we we're almost out of uh time
but but i wanted to ask you two more
techie questions for my own benefit well
because i don't really
i i sort of mapped that area but it's
kind of mapped as
terror incognito where i haven't done my
my deep research
um in and it's
where do you see like i've had
conversations with with gregory landor
from the regen network
and uh i know a few of the people
involved in
um holochain and um
enlighten me from your perspective where
those two pieces sit
with earth bank and and would you
see them as um doing something in
parallel or
is there a possible collaboration yeah
yeah definitely and you know had we've
had many good
chats with gregory uh and also christian
uh
and you know we we do have a
a partnership uh with with uh regen
network so the liquid token tokenization
sort of software
with with regen so you know we think
that
what the ecological
state verification protocols is going to
be a cool collaboration with them
uh and i guess what we're doing is kind
of
the financial systems architecture
um we do have some of our own kind of
verification
models but where our resolution
and where we're at is is is a different
area of verification to what they're
doing so you know we have to verify
certain amount of things
and what regen network are doing is like
super
detailed you know um you know like
looking at um a wheat farm you know and
no-till agriculture like very like
they're honing in with such specific
specificity which is great um
because we can draw on that knowledge
base and it's an open source
architecture which is cool and you know
we'll be contributing to open source
uh information architecture and also
machine
learning algorithms as well as we go to
kind of be part of the open source
movement as well so you know it's very
much a plug and play
where we can collaborate with region
network to draw upon the information
base and data that they're gathering and
developing
and organizing um and we it can
certainly
be part of helping inform our decision
metrics
and you know financial investment
decisions that we package up into
products
for other banks or other financial
institutions
so that's pretty cool holochain we've
definitely you know
been admirers of what they're trying to
do and you know we um
uh actually one of our uh uh
key team members uh edward he's he's
been
a little bit involved within that his
collaboration software
uh actually got bought out by uh
holochain
so um so that so our director of
strategy actually built
uh a software product for collaboration
that holochain is now using
and you know working on to increase the
sort of collaborative abilities um that
the holochain can
offer to the world which is cool so
we'll be able to plug in there as well
yeah there's been a little bit of sort
of
somewhat polemic against blockchain from
people
um working in in holochain and i'm not
quite understanding the details about it
like somehow
i i was reminded of the early battles
when electricity was um starting to
roll out between are we going to for the
ac system or the dc system and and we
unfortunately went for the um ac system
and
and wasted a lot of energy in the
process and if we had listened to
tesla rather than edison um the the
world would have taken quite a
different turn and is it really
analogous to
to the conversation building all these
platforms
on the blockchain or or working with the
the more distributed sort of
biometrically informed
holochain approach uh do you do you see
it quite as
fundamental as a baseline decisions
really high upstream
or can the two actually some
form a symbiosis where you where you can
use holochain technology in the context
of blockchain
yeah and i i think you know that's a
good question and
it's it's a pretty complex landscape
which is
constantly evolving you know month by
month something is changing and
something new is emerging in this
very dynamic area so i i can't speak in
absolutes but i can say that
from a sort of evolutionary emergent
property perspective that
that what blockchain is representing
from a decentralization perspective and
what holochain is representing in the
sort of distributed ledger
so it's a distributed ledger technology
and not a blockchain
but blockchain is a distributed ledger
technology so
um so you could say that broadly we have
distributed ledger technologies
and one of which a subset is blockchain
now
blockchain can you know do all sorts of
things that
are automating functions that are now
manual so
that's kind of a pretty cool thing that
you know if we want to like scale up
regenerative agriculture and program
money
to achieve regenerative outcomes you
know blockchain can be very handy for
that
uh it doesn't mean it's the only tool
because in the tool set you have
distributed ledger technologies
with which holochain is one um so you
know
they're all tools um in the toolbox
that we can choose from to achieve the
outcomes
um and i try not to you know blockchain
is one of many tools you know we're
really big fans of open banking
technology now open banking technology
is not powered by blockchain but it's
it's committed to the
principles of transparency uh and
interoperability
um now so you know so we
so a lot of what the work we're doing
right now is is
is actually not uh involving so much on
blockchain because
right now there's a lot of technology
constraints and bottlenecks with
blockchain
that has meant that it hasn't really
scaled
to the sort of internet of money that
it's it's proposing to be
and so from our perspective there's a
whole bunch of sort of
system conditions and sort of um
i guess path dependencies that haven't
yet been addressed in our
you know perspective from the first
principles uh
you know where blockchain is at is right
now is it's it's still very early days
it's got huge potential obviously uh
enterprise blockchain
has had a lot of uptake recently in
banks um in everything from
supply chains uh and so in that sense
blockchain is kind of a little bit like
what open source software
was like people said ah open source
software it's not really a thing
like how can you do that but yet right
now open source software is self-evident
it became not just a movement it
literally powered a lot of
the big technology companies you see
today and just like right now
machine learning algorithms the best are
usually
open source you know that are used you
know
conventionally um in industry um and
academia
particularly so so we can say that
blockchain is a bit like
open source software right now that in
the beginning people saying oh this
thing you know
it's a little bit too hard it's not
going to work you know it doesn't but i
think what's going to evolve over time
is open
architecture that's interoperable um and
these are all part
of that you know um
one final question really um i mean i
could go on forever because there's so
much interesting things to learn from
you and
with you there's underlying this whole
really positive intent that is basically
saying
wouldn't it be wonderful if the
guardians of the land whether they're
farmers
um peasant farmers anywhere in the world
or indigenous
people still maintaining um
the ecosystems that they
deeply believe they belong to rather
than the ecosystems belonging to them
which is a kind of
real shift that i think we need to make
and come back to understand yes
we belong to the land um
i know that there's lots of people in
this field who are really trying hard
to funnel investment and funds to
support
the people who are caring for improving
bioproductivity and healthy ecosystems
restoration and
ecosystems functions but and
for me there's a little bit of a
question where when i look at
the sort of proof of change
of state or change of state protocols
regen
and and all all these attempts of
bringing in
high technology whether it's through
local sensors
or using digital remote imagery and then
um working algorithms that that use that
data
to to prove what's going on in the
ground are we not in danger of
now connecting this vast amount of
peasant farmers who are still
caring for land around the world and the
the indigenous people
to a technology
that the only way to access the money
is through the technology and the
technology is going to change them as
soon as they
are forced to use it and similarly if
they're
gift cultures that have been evolving
over a
very very long time frame the
the kind of colonialization of the mind
that comes in with the use of technology
and maybe also would come in with the
influx of
suddenly a lot more money that then
than their self-sufficiency systems have
needed
for millennia um isn't there
a slight danger that we're actually
in the best of intentions to serve could
have
negative side effects or in an even more
extreme way
that by building the technology that
would allow
um social and ecological capital to
then through just a formula trans
be transferred into financial capital
that we're actually
with the best of intentions suddenly not
noticing that the flip side of that coin
could be used
to drive the largest form of enclosure
yet
of the the remaining comments um where
do you
like it for me that's a really sticky
point and
what do you sit with that yeah it's yeah
the the the risks you talk of are very
real
and and i take them very
seriously that that we need to address
and
you know for one thing i i think all
technology companies
all technology companies
and particularly ones that are going to
have systemic influence uh
needs to hire bioethicists
need to hire applied cultural
anthropologists
need to hire the best people
the best minds and the best parts
honestly
because what you're talking about there
is very much about
you know uh mind heart soul integrity
of communities that you know some are
uncontacted tribes in the amazon
some are deeply
[Music]
uh regenerative cultures that are so in
tune
so in sync with their environment and
indeed the cosmos the
movement of the moon and the planets and
are still there
and connected and technology can
absolutely take them away from that and
i think
like when we're in costa rica last year
and met
um an elder you know who
he had he they brought some cacao that
they'd grown in
jungle rainforest and said you know we
need your help
um because and this was in an area of
costa rica where 1.5
of the entire world's biodiversity is in
that
like particular area of costa rica it's
mind-blowing
you know and so these people they embody
all of that knowledge and more
and so he was saying this was saying you
know the kids are getting onto the
mobile phones and they're just like
they're it's like sucking their
attention
like and from his perspective you know
and world view it's like sucking a
spirit right and so that is kind of a
thing that
you know and a lot of people in silicon
valley have observed but
our relationship with technology is not
healthy
you know they've created a monster and
so we need to address that monster
for me it's partially i've been thinking
about this a lot lately and because
like it's it's sort of you know i did
these um
sdg community implementation flashcards
and
my work with guy education and one of
the the sort of design
briefs that i set myself working with
them is like i wanted to create a tool
the use of which which
would change the way people think like
following bucky fuller's advice that
don't
don't tell people what to think if you
want to check them to change their mind
give them a tool the use of which will
change the way they think
and then suddenly um maybe about a year
ago
it occurred to me that if you really sit
with that sentence and you really pay
attention to it then
all our technologies starting with the
printing press and certainly with the
computers we're using to talk to each
other
are changing the way we think sometimes
for the better sometimes
for the worst but we really need to be
careful
of that power of technology to
colonialize
us and and change us and and the the
stirring into that skid um taking a
piece
of advice from from the the poet
scientist
who sees who everywhere doesn't see
nature
anywhere in the right light i actually
think we need to reframe
technology and understand that there are
technologies of the sacred that the
aboriginal elders you were talking about
beginning of this conversation have been
guarding for 10
000 years and these technologies are
more powerful than anything that has
come out of silicon valley
and similarly if everything is nature
we have to include all our crude
mechanistic technology
into that larger container but then also
understand
that and if your father like just
being with the magic of two
cells meeting and then over nine months
inside a womb
turning into this creature that that
that suddenly sees the light of
this this world and then watching this
creature transform over the last
tomorrow's my daughter's third birthday
and
you you just look at technology and you
say like we're so arrogant to believe
that
that that what we call high technology
has
even the slightest to hold again against
the real true technology
of of of um the wider system that we're
part of of life
so i think it's about reframing
technology in that larger context and
and and being humble about what
technology actually can achieve
and what it's for and then really having
ethical conversations around
what technologies to use when when and
which ones not to use
and that that will be part of our
um right of passage as a species to
whether we're actually going to make it
um through this i have the needle oh
i 100 agree that's the it's this
technology and our relationship with it
and our ability and our ability to
wisely
uh wield such tools uh in the right way
is is i agree is going to decide whether
the fate of the human species becomes a
footnote
in sort of gaia's uh experiments or
if we you know we tried they didn't
quite work out as humans but
or maybe we could work out and maybe we
could flourish
into uh wonderful uh beings that were
obviously meant to be so
i really hope that we can get there and
um like you said you need to refrain
i'm deeply grateful that you are out
there doing the work you do and that
makes me hopeful that we can actually
um take that second path here just spoke
to that
that we we still have a role to play we
can be
um intelligent heartfelt compassionate
loving keystone species that celebrate
life in the way that we
ought to because we're an expression of
it so let's let's keep working towards
this and
wonderful to talk to you and i look
forward to learning more about earth
bank as
it develops have a wonderful rest of the
day thank you so much
daniel it's wonderful to be with you
again
speak again soon bye